<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be enquired of within the diocesse of Chester, in the visitation of the reuerende father in God, William Bishop of Chester in the xxij yeere of the reigne of our most gratious soueraigne Lady Elizabeth &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Chester. Bishop (1579-1595 : Chaderton)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00168</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10174.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2635</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24401707</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24401707</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27638</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00168)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27638)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1850:76)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be enquired of within the diocesse of Chester, in the visitation of the reuerende father in God, William Bishop of Chester in the xxij yeere of the reigne of our most gratious soueraigne Lady Elizabeth &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Chester. Bishop (1579-1595 : Chaderton)</author>
                  <author>Chaderton, William, 1540?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Christopher Barker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1580?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint date suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title within illustrated border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27638:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27638:1"/>
            <p>Articles to be enquired of within the Dioceſſe of Cheſter, in the viſitation of the <hi>reuerende father in GOD,</hi> William Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the xxij yeere of the reigne of our moſt gratious ſoueraigne Lady Elizabeth. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes Maieſtie.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon with angel holding book and quill on one side and eagle on the other side</figDesc>
                  <head>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of woman with shield and flaming sword</figDesc>
                  <head>FIDES</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of woman holding sheep</figDesc>
                  <head>HVMILITAS</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of lion with wings and bull with wings</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:27638:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27638:2"/>
            <head>Articles.</head>
            <p n="1"> 
               <note place="margin">Church and Churchyards.</note> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, whether your Church, Chappel, or Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell be well and ſufficiently repayred, and clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, kept, and the manſion houſe of your Parſon or Vicar, with the buildings thereunto belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, likewiſe well and ſufficiently repayred, and your Churchyard well fenſed, and clenly kept? And if any default be made in the premiſſes: or your ſayde Church, Chappell, or Churchyarde be abuſed or prophaned by any vnlawfull, or vnſeemely acte, game, or exerciſe, as by Lordes of miſrule, Summer lordes, or ladies, Pipers, Ruſhebearers, Moricedancers, Pedlers, Bearewardes, and ſuch like. Then through whoſe default, and what be the names of the offenders in that behalfe.</p>
            <p n="2"> 
               <note place="margin">Waxe,</note> 2 Whether any man hath pulled downe, or diſcouered any Church, Chauncell, or Chappell, or any part of any of them, any church Porche, Veſtry, or Steeple, Almeſhouſe, Churchhouſe, or ſuch like, or haue pulled downe any belles, or haue felled or ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led any wood, or tymber in any churchyardes?</p>
            <p n="3"> 
               <note place="margin">The benefice.</note> 3 Whether your pariſh church be now vacant, or deſtitute of an incumbent, or no? Whether any Chappell where diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice hath accuſtomed to be ſaid vſually, be without a Curate or no? And if they be, how long haue they bene ſo, and who is the Patrone, and who occupieth the parſonage, or vicarage houſe with the glebe lande, and taketh other the tythes and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties belonging to the ſame?</p>
            <p n="4"> 
               <note place="margin">The parſonage</note> 4 Whether any vitailing, tippling, or ale ſelling be kept, or vſed within the manſion houſe of any parſon or vicar.</p>
            <p n="5"> 
               <note place="margin">Neceſſary or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments.</note> 5 Whether you haue in your churche or chappell all thinges neceſſary, and requiſite for common prayer and adminiſtration of the holy ſacramentes, ſpecially the booke of common prayer with the newe kalender, the Pſalter, the Bible of the largeſt vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, the Homilies, both firſt and ſecond tome, Eraſmus Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſis tranſlated into Engliſh, or for want thereof, Marlorates expoſition vpon S. Matthewes Goſpell, A comely and decent table ſtanding on a frame for the Communion table, with a faire linnen cloth to lay vpon the ſame, and ſome couering of ſilke,
<pb facs="tcp:27638:3"/>
buckram or other ſuch like for the cleane keeping thereof; a faire and comely communion cuppe of ſyluer, and a couer of ſiluer for the ſame, a comely large ſurples with wyde ſleeues, A ſure cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with two lockes and keyes for keeping of the Regiſter booke and all other things neceſſary for the premiſſes, with a comely pulpit conueniently placed, and alſo a cheſt or box for the poore?</p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin">Altars de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced.</note>6 Whether in your churches and chappels all altars be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly taken downe and cleane remoued euen vnto the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the place where they ſtoode paued, and the wall whereunto they ioyned whyted ouer, and made vniforme with the reſt, ſo as no breach or rupture appeare, And whether your Roode loftes be taken downe and altered, ſo that the vpper partes thereof with the ſoller or lofte be quite taken downe vnto the croſſe beame, &amp; that the ſaid beame haue ſome conuenient creaſt put vpon the ſame?</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">Implements vnlawfull.</note>7 Whether all and euery Antiphoners, Maſſe bookes, Grailes, porteſſes, proceſſionals, manuals, legendaries, and all other bookes of late belonging to your church or chappel, which ſerued for the ſuperſticious Latine ſeruice, be vtterly defaced, rent, and aboliſhed, and if they be not, through whoſe default that is, and in whoſe keeping they remaine? And whether all veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, albes, tunicles, ſtoles, phanons, pixes, paxes, handbels, ſacringbelles, cenſers, chriſmatories, croſſes, candleſtickes, holy waterſtickes, Images, and ſuch other reliques, and monuments of ſuperſtition and idolatrie bee vtterly defaced, broken and deſtroyed: And if not, where, and in whoſe cuſtody they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine?</p>
            <p n="8">
               <note place="margin">Seruice.</note>8 Whether common prayer be vſed in your church or chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell vpon Sondayes and holy dayes at conuenient houres, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, diſtinctly, and in ſuch order without any kinde of altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as is appointed by the booke of common prayer, and the lawes of this Realme? And whether your Miniſter ſo turne him ſelfe and ſtande in ſuch place of your church or chauncell, as the people may beſt heare the ſame? And whether your Parſon or Vicar do once euery quarter, at the leaſt, in his owne proper per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſaye diuine ſeruice, and adminiſter the Sacramentes, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:27638:3"/>
a ſurpleſſe according vnto the Queenes Iniunctions and the lawes of this Realme? And whether the holy Sacramentes be duely and reuerently miniſtred in ſuch maner as is ſet foorth by the ſame booke? And whether your Miniſter at al times vpon Sundayes and holy dayes, do we are in time of diuine ſeruice &amp; adminiſtration of the Sacraments, the ſurpliſſe yea or no, or doe ſuffer any other to ſaye the common prayer, or miniſter either of the Sacraments in your Church, not wearing the ſame?</p>
            <p n="9"> 
               <note place="margin">Preaching,</note> 9 Whether your Parſon or Vicar be a preacher allowed, and hath preached, or cauſed to be preached foure ſermons at the leaſt euery yeere in your church, and what bee the names of him or thoſe that ſo did preache, and whether they were lawfully licenſed ſo to preache, if any other then your Parſon or Vicar did preache the ſame? And whether if there be no Sermon, your Miniſter do reade for the moſt part euery ſunday diſtinctly and plainely, ſome part of the Homilies appointed to be read, and the Queenes In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions euery quarter of a yeere or no?</p>
            <p n="10"> 
               <note place="margin">Catechiſme</note> 10 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, do euery Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye and holy daye openly in the Church, call for, heare, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, all the children, apprentiſes, and ſeruantes of both ſexes that be of conuenient age within your pariſh, or at the leaſt ſo many of them by courſe as the time will ſerue, and as hee may well heare and inſtruct for halfe an houre at the leaſt, before or at the euening prayer, in the tenne Commandements, the Articles of the beliefe, and the Lordes prayer, and diligently examine and teache them the Catechiſme, as it is nowe laſt allowed and ſet forth? And whether for that purpoſe doth hee take the names of them all, and by courſe call certaine of them by name euery ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day and holy daye, to come to learne the ſame Catechiſme?</p>
            <p n="11"> 
               <note place="margin">Superſtition &amp; innouation,</note> 11 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, or any other within your Pariſh, be a fauourer of the Romiſh church or reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or hath or doth mainteine or teache and doctrine contrarie or repugnant to any of the Articles agreed vpon by the Clergie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conuocation holden at London, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1562. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue publikely or ſecretly taught and doctrine tending to the diſcredit and diſpraiſe either of the booke of Common
<pb facs="tcp:27638:4"/>
prayer, or of the Preachers and Miniſters of the word and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or of the receiued order for gouernement in the Church of England, or make any other Innouation? And whether they haue permitted any man ſo teaching or making ſuch innouatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? And whether any keepe and ſecret conuenticles, preachings, lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or readings, or priuate Communions, contrary to the law, and what be their names?</p>
            <p n="12">
               <note place="margin">Curate.</note>12 Whether any perſon or perſons not being ordered at the leaſt for a Deacon, or licenſed by the Ordinarie, do ſaye Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prayer openly in your Church or Chappell, or any not being at the leaſt a Deacon, do ſolemnize Matrimonie or adminiſter the Sacraments, and what he or they be that ſo do? And whether the Parſon, Vicar, or Farmer of your benefice, do cauſe or ſuffer any Curate to ſerue your Churche before he be examined and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Ordinary or his deputie in writing, and ſhew the ſame to the Churchwardens.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <note place="margin">Communion.</note>13 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate hath admitted any to the receiuing of the holy Communion aboue xx. yeeres of age that cannot ſaie by heart the Catechiſme, the Lordes prayer, the Articles of the faith, and the ten Commaundementes in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe, or any aboue xiiii. yeeres of age and vnder xx. that cannot ſaye the Catechiſme ſet forth in the booke of common prayer, or hath admitted any of any other pariſh to receiue the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion without reaſonable cauſe or ſpeciall licenſe of their own miniſter? or whether hath he admitted to receiue the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and open and notorious blaſphemer, fornicatour, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, drunkard, or euill liuer, by whom the Congregation is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, without dewe penaunce firſt done to the ſatiſfaction of the congregation, or any malicious perſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is notoriouſly knowen to be out of charitie, or that hath done any open wrong to his neighbour by worde or deede, without dewe reconciliation firſt made to the partie that is wronged?</p>
            <p n="14">
               <note place="margin">Baptiſme.</note>14 Whether your Font be ſweetly kept and renewed from time to time with cleane and freſh water, and whether any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter leauing the vſe of the Font, do Chriſten or Baptize in any baſons or other prophane veſſels not cuſtomablie vſed in the
<pb facs="tcp:27638:4"/>
Church before time? Or whether your Miniſter do Baptize or Chriſten any out of the face of the Church and Congregation, &amp; at any other time then vpon Sundayes or holy dayes without ſpeciall cauſe, or without Godfathers and Godmothers, &amp; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any perſon or perſons bee admitted to anſwere as Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers or Godmothers at the Chriſtening of any childe, except hee or ſhee haue before receiued the holy Communion, and can ſaye by heart the Articles of the Chriſtian faith, the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and the Lordes praier, and will recite the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Miniſter if he or ſhe be thereunto required?</p>
            <p n="15"> 
               <note place="margin">Regiſter of Chriſtenings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 15 Whether the Regiſter booke of all Chriſtenings, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages and Burials that happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in your pariſh from time to time, be duely kept: and the ſame Chriſteninges, Mariages, and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, entred into the ſame booke by your Miniſter according to the Queenes Maieſties Iniunctions?</p>
            <p n="16"> 
               <note place="margin">Mariage.</note> 16 Whether your miniſter hath maried any perſons priuatly in any houſe or corner out of the Church or face of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, or the Banes not being thriſe ſolemnelie on three Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies or holy dayes aſked in the pariſh Church where ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons dwelled, or any ſuch perſon or perſons maried at any other pariſh church or chappell? And whether your miniſter hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried any Infantes, or children vnder age, or any within the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees prohibited by Gods lawes and the lawes of this Realme, or any that hath a huſband or wife liuing, and if he haue done ſo, then who be the parties, &amp; who were preſent at any ſuch mariage, and in what place was the ſame ſolemnized?</p>
            <p n="17"> 
               <note place="margin">Churching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> women.</note> 17 Whether your Miniſter do Church any vnmaried wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, after they haue bene deliuered of their children begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully, before they haue acknowledged their faultes openly, according to the order preſcribed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ordinarie or his deputie?</p>
            <p n="18"> 
               <note place="margin">Viſitation of the ſicke and Buriall.</note> 18 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate be diligent in viſiting the ſicke, and comforting them, and do moue them ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, eſpecially when they make their teſtaments, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the neede of the poore, and to giue to their boxe or cheſt their charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deuotion? And whether they burie the dead without any popiſh ceremonies or ſuperſtition in ſuch Chriſtian and comely
<pb facs="tcp:27638:5"/>
maner as is preſcribed by the booke of Common prayer?</p>
            <p n="19">
               <note place="margin">Perambulation.</note>19 Whether for the reteining of the perambulation of the circuit of your pariſh, the Miniſter and Clarke with the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens and certaine of the ſubſtanciall men of the pariſh, in the dayes of Rogacions, walke about your pariſh according to the Queenes Maieſties Iniunctions? And whether doe they vſe in ſuch perambulation any banners, croſſes, handbelles, or any ſuch like popiſh ceremonies, other then is preſcribed and permitted by the booke of common prayer and the lawes of this Realme?</p>
            <p n="20">
               <note place="margin">Admonition to the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens.</note>20 Whether for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> putting of the churchwarde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; ſworneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the better in remembrance of their duetie in obſeruing and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch as offend in not comming to diuine ſeruice, your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter or Reader do openly euery Sunday, after he haue read the ſecond leſſon at morning &amp; euening prayer, moniſh &amp; warne the Churchwardens and ſworne men, to looke to their charge in this behalfe, and to obſerue who contrarie to the ſaid ſtatute offende in abſenting them ſelues negligently or wilfully from their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church or Chappell, or vnreuerently as is aforeſaid, vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in time of diuine ſeruice?</p>
            <p n="21">
               <note place="margin">Pluralities.</note>21 Whether hath your Parſon or Vicar any moe benefices or ſpirituall promotions then one, how many, and in what coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie be they, what are their names, and who is the Patrone of euery of them?</p>
            <p n="22">
               <note place="margin">Reſidence.</note>22 Whether is your Parſon or Vicar reſident, and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his benefice or no? if he be reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whether doth he keepe the parſonage or vicarage with the glebe and other his tithes &amp; commodities in his owne handes, or doth he demiſe the ſame or any part thereof to his Patrone or any other perſon or perſons? what parcels are ſo demiſed, to whom, &amp; for what rent? if he be not reſident, or abſent aboue lxxx. dayes in the yeere, then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he demiſe his benefice to his Curate? and if he be able to diſpend xx. pound by yeere, doth he diſtribute the fourtieth part thereof yeerely to the poore of the pariſh or no?</p>
            <p n="23">
               <note place="margin">Symonie.</note>23 Whether you Parſons or Vicars haue come to their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices by any Symonie, fraude or deceipte, or by any confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or agreement of friends, or by any other bond, compoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:27638:5"/>
or agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or by any other colourable pact, or vnlawfull meane whatſoeuer, or be vehemently ſuſpected or defamed therof? And whether in performance of any ſuch pact, couenaunt or promiſe, there hath bene any bond or leaſe made betweene the Patrone &amp; Incumbent directly or indirectly?</p>
            <p n="24"> 
               <note place="margin">Suſpected women.</note> 24 Whether your Parſon, Vicar or Curate, do keepe any ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected woman in his houſe, or be an incontinent perſon, giuen to dronkenneſſe or idlenes, or be a haunter of Tauernes, Alehou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or ſuſpected places, a Hunter, Hauker, Dicer, carder, Tabler, Swearer, or otherwiſe giue any euill example of life? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his apparell bee comely and graue as becommeth his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and function?</p>
            <p n="25"> 
               <note place="margin">Pariſh Clarke</note> 25 Whether the Pariſh Clarke be appointed according to the auncient cuſtome of the pariſh? And whether hee be not obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, eſpecially in the time of celebration of diuine ſeruice, or of the Sacramentes, or in any preparation thereunto? And whether he be able &amp; ready to reade the firſt Leſſon, the Epiſtle, and the Pſalmes with anſwere to the ſuffragies as is vſed, and whether he keepe not the bookes and ornamentes of the Church faire and cleane, &amp; cauſe the church &amp; quier, the Communion table, the Pulpit and the Font, to bee made decent and cleane againſt the feruice time, the Communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Sermon, and Baptiſme?</p>
            <p n="26"> 
               <note place="margin">Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens.</note> 26 Whether haue your Churchwardens aſſiſted your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in his office and function fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time, and whether haue they done their diligence to bring ſuch into the Church as ſtand gazing &amp; talking in the Churchyard, or frequent &amp; lurke in Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes or tippling houſes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of diuine ſeruice, &amp; whether haue they bene careful and diligent to ſee good order and ſilence kept in the Church during the time of Sermons &amp; Seruice, and whether haue they diligently noted the names of all ſuch parties euery Sunday and holy daye, as haue bene abſent from diuine ſeruice at any time, and leuied the forfaiture of xii. pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for euery abſence from common prayer, according to the ſtatute, and put the ſame to the vſe of the poore of the pariſh? And if they haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n any of the premiſſes, then howe often haue they ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended,
<pb facs="tcp:27638:6"/>
and what be their names, and what particular ſummes of mony haue bene forfeited that waye, and by whome, ſince the laſt viſitation, and howe much of ſuch forfeitures haue bene leuied by the Churchwarde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and by them deliuered to the vſe of the poore of the pariſh, and to whom hath the ſame bene deliuered?</p>
            <p n="27">
               <note place="margin">Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens accompt.</note>27 Whether your Churchwardens haue yeerely giuen an accompt of the Church goodes committed to their charge, and of other their receipts and expenſes? And whether haue they ſold any bels or other church goodes without conſent of the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie fiſt had in writing? And whether haue they employed all ſuch goodes, receiptes, and ſummes of mony, to the vſe of the church or no? and what be the names of the offenders?</p>
            <p n="28">
               <note place="margin">Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</note>28 Whether the Churchwardens and ſworne men in former yeeres, haue of any priuate corrupt affection concealed any crime or other diſorder done in their times, and haue not preſented the ſame, and if ſo, then what faultes haue they ſo concealed, &amp; what were the names of ſuch Churchwardens and ſworne men, ſo concealing the ſame?</p>
            <p n="29">
               <note place="margin">Collectors for the poore.</note>29 Whether haue ye Collectors for the poore of the Pariſh, and whether do they their duetie in gathering and diſtributing the Almes of the Pariſhioners, and whether haue any Collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors any money in their handes not acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted for, or not beſtowed vpon the poore? And whether be there any of abilitie within your pariſh, that wilfully or obſtinatly refuſe to giue reaſonably to the reliefe of the poore?</p>
            <p n="30">
               <note place="margin">Ringing and tolling of bels.</note>30 Whether when any Chriſtian bodie is in paſſing, the bell be tolled to moue the people to praye for the ſicke perſon, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the greater townes where the ſicke perſon dwelleth nere vnto the Church, and whether after the tyme of his or their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of this world, there be any more ringing but one ſhort peale before the buriall, and another ſhort peale after the buriall? And whether on all Saintes day after Euening prayer, there be any ringing at all in your Church or Chappell, or any other ſuperſticious ceremonies vſed, tending to the maintenance of the Popiſh purgatorie or prayer for the dead, and who they bee that vſe or doe the ſame? And whether there be any ringing on
<pb facs="tcp:27638:6"/>
Sondaies or holy dayes in the ſeruice time, or betweene Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning prayer and the Letanie, or at any other times, contrarie to good order or Lawe?</p>
            <p n="31"> 
               <note place="margin">Scholema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note> 31 What Scholemaſters haue you within your Pariſh or Chappelrie, that teache either ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly or priuately in any ſchoole, gentlemans houſe or els where, and whether be they of good &amp; ſincere religion, and licenſed by the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe to teach, in writing vnder his ſeale, and whether bee they diligent in teaching and bringing vp youth, and to inſtruct them in godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and vertue, and eſpecially in Maſter Nowels Catechiſme lately ſet forth? And whether teache they any thing contrarie to the religion now godlily eſtabliſhed, or do not cauſe their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reſort vnto the Church to heare diuine ſeruice &amp; Sermons?</p>
            <p n="32"> 
               <note place="margin">Deanes Rural and Sumners</note> 32 Whether the Archdeacon, Chancellor, Commiſſarie, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall, or any other vſing Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction in this Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, their regiſters or actuaries, Apparitors or Sumners, haue at any time winked at, and ſuffered any adulteries, fornications, inceſtes, or other faultes or offences, to paſſe and remaine vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and vncorrected, for money, rewardes, bribes, pleaſure, friendſhip, or any other parciall or affectionate reſpect? or haue permitted any penance without ſpecial licence of his Ordinarie?</p>
            <p n="33"> 
               <note place="margin">Maſters and Dames.</note> 33 Whether all fathers, mothers, maſters &amp; dames of your pariſh, cauſe their children, ſeruants, and apprentices, both man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde and womankinde, being aboue ſix yeeres of age, and vnder twenty, which haue not learned the Cathechiſme, to come to the church on the Sundayes &amp; holy dayes, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> times to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or at the leaſt ſuch or ſo many of them as your Miniſter ſhall appoint, and there diligently and obediently to heare, and to bee ordered by the miniſter, vntill ſuch time as they haue learned the ſame Catechiſme, and what bee the names of thoſe that doe not cauſe their children, ſeruants and apprentices, ſo to come to the Church to be inſtructed and examined?</p>
            <p n="34"> 
               <note place="margin">Abſents from the Church.</note> 34 Whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of your pariſh, eſpecially houſholders, hauing no lawful excuſe to be abſent, do faithfully and dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly endeauour them ſelues to reſort with their children, and ſeruants, to their pariſh Church or Chappell, on the holydayes, &amp; chiefly
<pb facs="tcp:27638:7"/>
vpon Sundayes, to Morning and Euening prayer, and then &amp; there abide orderly &amp; ſoberly during the time of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayer, Homilies, Preachings, and other ſeruice of God there vſed, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and deuoutly giuing them ſelues to the hearing thereof, &amp; who they be that either negligently or wilfully abſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, or come very late to the Church vpon Sundayes eſpecially, and how long hath any of your pariſh abſented him ſelfe from his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church, or who be they that walke, talke, or otherwiſe vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently behaue them ſelues in the Church, or vſe any gaming abroade, or paſtime in any houſe, or ſit in the ſtreetes or Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde, or in any Tauerne or Alehouſe vpon the Sunday or holy daye in the time of Common prayer, Sermon, or reading of the Homilies, either before noone or after noone?</p>
            <p n="35">
               <note place="margin">Not Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating.</note> 35 Whether there be any in your pariſh, man or woman, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of conuenient age, that hath not receiued the holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion thriſe at the leaſt this laſt yeere, and namely at Eaſter laſt (or thereabout) for once, and what be their names, and for what cauſe in your iudgement they do abſteine from the holy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion? and whether any haue receiued the holy Communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any other pariſh Church or Chappell then their owne, and for what cauſes in your opinion?</p>
            <p n="36">
               <note place="margin">Chriſtnings out of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</note> 36 Whether do you know any ſuch parentes, hauing children borne that were not Chriſtened at their own pariſh Church, and for what cauſe they haue not bene ſo Chriſtened there, or do you know, haue heard, or vehemently ſuſpect any ſuch pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, whoſe children haue bene Chriſtened by any Popiſh prieſt, or otherwiſe then is now lawfully allowed by her Maieſties Lawes and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions?</p>
            <p n="37">
               <note place="margin">Suppreſſors of Teſtaments.</note> 37 Whether there be any within your pariſh that miniſter the goodes of thoſe which be dead without lawfull authoritie, or any that ſuppreſſe the teſtamentes or laſt will of the dead, or any executor that hath not fulfilled the Teſtators will, eſpecially ſuch as haue not diſcharged ſuch legacies as are bequeathed to the Church, or to Orphanes, poore maides mariages, highwayes, ſchooles, or other godly vſes, and what be their names?</p>
            <p n="38">
               <note place="margin">Teſtaments not proued.</note> 38 Whether do you knowe any houſholder or other perſon
<pb facs="tcp:27638:7"/>
whatſoeuer, within your Pariſh or Chappelrie, that is deceaſed, that haue made their laſt willes &amp; Teſtament and the ſame not hitherto proued nor adminiſtration taken, from the Ordinarie or other Iudge competent, of the goodes, debtes, and cattals of the ſaid decedent? if any ſuch be, expreſſe their names, &amp; of them who vnlawfully do deteyne any the ſaid goodes, debts, or cattals.</p>
            <p n="39"> 
               <note place="margin">The othe for an Inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarie.</note> 39 Whether doth your Deane Rural, vſually ſweare al ſuch executors and adminiſtrators that proue Teſtaments, or take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations before him, to exhibite a true and perfect Inuenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of all ſuch goods, debts, and cattalles, as euery ſuch perſon died poſſeſſed of, or for any priuate reſpectes forbeareth to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſuch oth vnto them, and whether do you know or haue heard your Deane hath done ſo at any time?</p>
            <p n="40"> 
               <note place="margin">Leaſes not pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries.</note> 40 Whether do you knowe any the Executors or Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators of any perſon or perſons deceaſed, that dwelled in your Pariſh or Chappelrie, that haue not inſerted all ſuch leaſe or lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or other demiſe for terme of one or moe yeeres, in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentarie of the goodes, debtes, and cattals of the ſaid deceaſed, at ſuch time as they procured the ſaid Teſtamentes to be proued, or adminiſtration of the ſaid goodes to be to them orderly commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? or haue not procured the ſame leaſes to be priſed and valued among other the goodes and cattals of the ſaide decedent, for the benefite of the wife, children, or of others to whom the benefite of them ought to appertaine, and whether do you know, haue heard or beleeue, your Deane hath borne, winked at, or willingly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſuch leaſe or leaſes for his priuate commoditie, to be left out of the ſaid Inuentarie?</p>
            <p n="41"> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſpitals and Spittlehouſes</note> 41 Whether your Hoſpitalles, Spittles, and Almes houſes be well and godly vſed, according to the foundations and ancient ordinances of the ſame? whether there be any placed in them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the poore, impotent, and needy perſons, that haue not wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with or whereby to liue?</p>
            <p n="42"> 
               <note place="margin">Inceſt. &amp;c.</note> 42 Whether there be any that be maried in degrees forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, or that haue maried two wiues, or two huſbandes, both li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, or that liue not together with their wiues, and what be their names? any maried that haue made precontractes, any that haue
<pb facs="tcp:27638:8"/>
maried without banes thriſe ſolemnely aſked, or that haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried foorth of their pariſh Church, where they ought to haue ſolemnized mariage?</p>
            <p n="43">
               <note place="margin">Vſurers.</note>43 Whether any perſon or perſons within your pariſh, haue committed vſurie contrarie to an Act againſt vſurie, made in the xxxvii. yeere of the reigne of the late King Henry the eight, and lately reuiued, and what are the names of ſuch Vſurers? &amp; what is the maner of their vſurie?</p>
            <p n="44">
               <note place="margin">Sorcerie.</note>44 Whether there be any man or woman in your pariſh, that vſeth witchcraft, ſorcerie, charmes, or vnlawfull prayer, or inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations in Latin or Engliſh, or vpon any Chriſtian body or beaſt, or any that reſorteth to the ſame for councell or helpe, and what be their names?</p>
            <p n="45">
               <note place="margin">Alehouſes, Markets and Fayres.</note>45 Whether be there any Inkeepers, Alewiues, Vitailers, or Tipplers, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuffer or do admit any perſon or perſons in their houſes, to eate, drinke, or playe at Cardes, Tables, or ſuch like games in time of Common prayer, or Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the Sundays and holy dayes, and whether there bee any ſhops open on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes or holydayes, or be there any Butchers, Pedlars, or others that vſe to ſell meate and other thinges, in the time of Common prayer, Preaching, or reading of the Homilies? And whether in any Fayres or common Markets, falling on the Sunday, there be any ſhowing of any wares before the diuine ſeruice be done in the forenoone?</p>
            <p n="46">
               <note place="margin">Contention &amp; Drunkennes.</note>46 Whether there be in your Pariſh any that be malicious, contentious, or vncharitable perſons, ſeeking the vniuſt vexation of their neighbours, ſcoldes, common ſwearers, or blaſphemers of the name of God, any fornicatours, adulterers, inceſtuous perſons, bawdes, or receuiours of ſuch incontinent perſons, or har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borers of women with childe which be vnmaried, conueying or ſuffering them to go away before they haue done any penance, or make ſatiſfaction to the congregation, or any perſons that are vehemently ſuſpected of ſuch faultes, or that be not of good name and fame touching ſuch crimes and faultes, any common drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerds, ribaudes, or other notorious euill liuers?</p>
            <p n="47">
               <note place="margin">Papiſtrie, Maſſe and Prieſtes.</note>47 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curat, openly or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately
<pb facs="tcp:27638:8"/>
ſaye maſſe or other ſeruice forbidden, or heare the ſame? And whether do you knowe any popiſh prieſtes or runnagate perſons, that do preach or miniſter the Sacraments otherwyſe then they are now vſed, or that doth vſe ſhrift and auricular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, or make haliwater, or halybread, or bleſſe palmes, or prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe any ſuch like Romiſh ceremonies, or do not frequent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayer, or els do reſort ſecretly or openly into your Pariſh. And whoſe houſe do they ſo reſort vnto, and of whom are they harbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp; what be the names of ſuch popiſh prieſtes or runnagates, &amp; ſuch as ſo harbour them? and whether know you any that keepe any ſecret conuenticles, readings, preachings, or lectures, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Lawe?</p>
            <p n="48"> 
               <note place="margin">Rebellious bookes.</note> 48 Whether be there any perſon or perſons, Eccleſiaſticall or Temporall within your pariſh, or els where within this Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, that of late hath reteined or kept in their cuſtody, or that reade, ſell, vtter, diſperſe, carrie, or deliuer to others, any Engliſh bookes, ſet forth of late yeeres at Louaine, or in any other place beyond the ſeas, by Harding, Dorman, Allen, Sanders, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton, Marſhall, Briſtow, or any of them, or by any other En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Papiſte, either againſt the Queenes Maieſties ſupremacie in matters Eccleſiaſticall, or againſt true Religion, and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like doctrine now receiued &amp; eſtabliſhed by common authoritie within this Realme, and what their names and ſurnames are?</p>
            <p n="49"> 
               <note place="margin">Beades and Primers.</note> 49 Whether be there any in our Pariſh that vſeth to praye in Engliſh or in Latin, vpon beades, or other ſuch like things, or vpon any ſuperſtitious popiſh Primer or other like booke, and what be their names?</p>
            <p n="50"> 
               <note place="margin">Adulterers.</note> 50 How many Adulteries, Inceſtes, and Fornications haue bene committed within your Pariſh or Chappelrie, ſince the laſt viſitation, and how many offenders in thoſe faultes haue bene put to penance and openly corrected?</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. Ceſtren.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
